To more public submissions on the Conservation Amendment Bill.
And we have our first submitter with us in person today, the New Zealand
Minerals Council. Josie, welcome.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you to open up, and then
we'll open up for questions. So over to you.
You're in luck because I thought I had 10 minutes.
I won't talk for long, and then you've got plenty of time for questions.
Thank you very much for the opportunity to speak to our written submission because
quite a lot of water's flowed under the bridge since then.
And just in case you don't know me, I'm Josie Goodall, the chief executive of the
New Zealand Minerals Council. We're a membership-based
organization that advocates for the mining industry in New
Zealand.
Provisions for the potential disposal or exchange of conservation
land have been removed from this bill, and we do contend that that wasn't
necessary.
There was a deliberate misinformation campaign about what that might mean,
and that is ongoing and threatens to derail this process,
and that should not be allowed to happen in our view.
It is important to modernize the laws around the use and management of
conservation land, and we continue to support that.
From the get-go, I'd like to make some things clear, and then, of course, I'm happy
to take questions.
Miners are not seeking privatization of conservation
land.
We are seeking a continuation of the system where miners are given
case-by-case access to conservation land on application
and where ownership stays with the Crown.
There may be occasions where disposal or exchange works for all
parties, and so it shouldn't be ruled out.
We support the strengthened economic focus of the bill, and
we see no evidence that this would undermine or shift away from the Department of
Conservation's management role, and neither would we want it to.
We think bans of use of land in the conservation estate are
unnecessary, and we reject the misinformation about mining on
the conservation estate.
Mining takes place on
0.04% of the conservation
estate.
Mining companies are paying users of the land and work with the landowners, which
is the Crown, on numerous conservation projects, as well as
funding others, and on infrastructure that has wider benefits, such as
road.
Important to note that the land use is temporary and the mine site is returned to
its natural state or as close as is possible at the end of the mine life.
In evidence of that, we submit the public recreation area of the
rehabilitated OceanaGold
Globe Progress mine site near Reefton on the West Coast of the
South Island.
This includes 22 kilometers of tracks to and within the previously
closed mine site, which is now a Department of Conservation
asset for visitors to the area. The Globe Hill
track and Globe Progress mine tracks and visitor
facilities include a shelter, interpretation
panels telling the story of the site, and toilets, and have been
developed by OceanaGold.
To quote DOC Greymouth district operations manager Chris
Hickford, "This area offers a unique look at the
mine site rehabilitation following mining activity.
It will be a great addition to the already popular visitor experiences
Reefton offers and attract people to the area.
The tracks have been built to deliver great opportunities for walkers and
bikers to get naturing." And that was a DOC press release of
19th September 2025.
The Department of Conservation is responsible for managing one-third of New
Zealand's land, and that is a big ask.
They do not have the resources to effectively manage that,
so some of the steps in this bill will help with that.
Those steps do not take away from the conservation values and the department's
functions.
Economic development and conservation management do not have to be mutually
exclusive, and in fact, taking advantage of economic
opportunities can enhance conservation with greater access to
funding and resources.
At the end of the day, the Department of Conservation has a land management role.
It is a government department, and the people who work there are public servants
who work for the government of the day.
Like any other land managers, they should be able to use all the tools in the shed
to do that job, better technology, and science and
evidence-based decision making.
We have submitted on the parts of the bill that impact commercial users of that
land, covering the intent of the bill, the functions of DOC, our
agreement that there needs to be streamlining of the management planning framework,
and the vital need to improve the concessions regime.
We have also asked for alignment of access provisions between the Conservation
Act and the Reserves Act, with two minor amendments to the Reserves
Act.
Getting alignment across many different pieces of legislation that cover mining is
ongoing work for us, and we appreciate it is often up to the land users to
point out where there are unintended consequences, which is what we've done with
that. And so I'm happy to take any questions.
Thank you, Josie. Thank you for that submission. Celia.
Thank you. Thank you, Josie. And I appreciate the
intent is for remediation, but I wondered if you'd ever
been to the Denniston Plateau.
Yes, I have.
And if you think about the
unique geological and
vegetation cover there,
do you think that's conceivable that that could be remediated?
I do, because I've visited the Bathurst Mine in that area, and
I've looked at and had explained to me the remediation work.
And what I'd really like people to know is there is a
huge team of people, and they work with the Department of Conservation, who
put a lot of thought into how they are going to
Return that site, and it's ongoing through the project life.
They do a lot of research into
what were the original native plants there, because some have been
overtaken by introduced plants.
Mm.
They do a lot of
pest and predator control, and they do things where they
can transfer plants and put them somewhere else for a while,
and then bring them back to where they were originally.
So there's a lot of work that goes into...
And it is a unique alpine environment.
The people who work there are very conscious of that.
As I say, they spend a lot of time thinking about, how can we
put this back to a unique alpine environment that no one even knows
we were here, basically.
Mm.
So,
I think there is a lot of misinformation. I think it's unfortunate.
I do encourage people to go and speak to the users of the
land.
And I know there is
an open letter of support of the Buller Plateau
Continuation project from a group on the West Coast,
who have also talk-- And this is the other thing that people need to consider.
These are regional economies in New Zealand.
Mm.
Some of them have had some pretty tough times.
At the moment, they've got a promise of some better times.
And so it's a whole equation. I
can hand on heart say that the people at Bathurst will be giving so
much attention to saving the right vegetation
and
looking after it and putting it back where they can.
And they're under so many regulations, and DOC watch them like a hawk.
So,
I think until you go there and look, and yes, you go and look and see
how it is now. And it is temporary land use.
So,
for my grandchild, he will go there when he's 30,
and
it will be like it is now, potentially. So...
Mm. Look, thank you. Cameron.
Oh, thank you very much. I've got a couple of questions, but I'll try and keep it
to one.
This exempt or pre-approved activities part of your submission, talking
about
making it a bit simpler
with all the overlapping
consents, applications, and concessions that one would have to do to set up a
project like this and with the remediation up front 30 years ahead.
It
talks about concessions for
access roads,
and other consents. How
much do you need this sort of
clear exemptions or pathways up
front? And how at the end of the process when remediation is
happening,
or the access is being
granted for walks and
experiences and tourism, and keeping that
concession at the end of the project as well, so the track can be maintained, so
that remediation can be ongoing and pest control and ecosystem
renewal.
Yeah. Very good question.
That whole process of that, yeah.
Yeah, and I think some of the other concession users have spoken to
surety around concessions of a timeframe.
So,
small country, not many people, not much money.
A lot of money
for development in New Zealand comes in from overseas.
And what the markets want is
some sort of indication that every three years they aren't going to have a rug
pulled out from under them. So, having a bit of longevity of concessions
for that infrastructure is quite important from an
investment point of view. As I've explained with
OceanaGold's Globe Progress project, in fact, that
infrastructure has been repurposed.
Well, actually, they built the cycle tracks.
So it's not the big baddie coming in from overseas.
These are collaborative long-term projects with the
community and DOC, if it's DOC land, of how are we going to
do this right. And I know that in the past there is some legacy
issues. But
we now have a lot of science and technology to
ensure that we can get it right, or if we don't get it right, we can
fix it. So, I think we have to trust modern day
versus legacy.
And no one is walking away from these.
OceanaGold has a commitment to that land forever.
And
so often, if DOC doesn't want the road or the track or whatever, or it
can't be repurposed, then it's negotiated as to
whether it's maintained or it's just left to
be overrun with vegetation or whatever.
So that's a DOC decision, really, how they continue to manage the land in
perpetuity.
Thank you. Priyanka.
Thank you.
Josie, you've mentioned that you support the strengthened focus of the
Amendment Bill on economic development on conservation land.
You've said you don't see that as a shift away from or
undermining of DOC's conservation function.
However, the wording in the bill does exactly that.
If you want an independent view on that, the Parliamentary Commissioner for the
Environment has laid it out really clearly in his submission.
He has said that using words like the greatest extent
practicable is an extremely high
statutory threshold. The lack of a hierarchy or prioritization
means that DOC would be almost told to
support economic development anywhere across the conservation land.
So, given you've said that you don't intend, you wouldn't support a shift away
from DOC's function, would you be supportive of a change in
the language or the wording in the bill to make it
clear that DOC's primary function is conservation?
So, that's the beauty of democracy, isn't it?
We're all sitting here discussing what happens to this bill, and there will be
negotiation. And so what we don't want
to see removed is an economic imperative, because we think it's
important that-
People come to this country and get access to national parks and don't have to pay.
Don't have to pay the park, don't have to pay anything.
That money, if they
had to pay, could go into keeping the
facilities and the land-
Yeah
...
in a good state. So the whole--
it's not
this terrible picture of strip malls
and-- that's just misinformation.
Sure.
So there has to be some economic imperative.
Yeah.
And I think it
sits equal, but it certainly shouldn't
undermine the purpose of conservation.
So you would support a change to the wording of the bill to ensure that
economic development within the bounds of a primary focus on
conservation
is allowed?
As long as it doesn't weaken the economic imperative.
Grant.
Yeah, just a quick question. So there's been a call from some to
think, "Well, just get rid of the whole bill.
It's all terrible," and all the rest of it. Any response to that?
Well, absolutely. As I say, we have to modernize legislation.
The original intent was so that the Department of Conservation
could actually get through their work in a way that didn't stress them
out completely by having a whole lot of permits that could
just be cookie cutter, because that's what they are, and to free up their
time to spend on the more complex
applications like ours.
And so that they could make a little bit of coin to pay for
some of this. They're not high on the list of
when the lollies are handed out at budget time,
and they've got a third of the country.
At least.
So,
something has to give here. So let's modernize the legislation,
make their life easier, have an opportunity that you can charge
for some things. If DOC wants to get rid of some of that land
because it's of no value to them, and there's a willing buyer
who's already using the land for a farm or whatever,
why shouldn't they be allowed to purchase that, and that money go back
into the
conservation coffers?
Thank you. Look, we've got time for one last question.
Lann is online with us. Lann.
Morena, Josie. Thank you so much for your submission today.
I don't know where to look at you.
Oh. Whatever screen works. Or not, it's totally sweet.
I wanted to pick up on Cameron's question about the
concession aspects, and because you have a line in your submission
about,
basically, if the concession regime gets in the way, it could have
far-reaching economic consequences.
For example, if a mining project was unable to
proceed. Do you accept that there
could also be far-reaching economic
consequences if, say, a super
large-scale mining project was to
proceed in the same way? That there's sort of costs and benefits both
ways?
I accept that that would be very thoroughly analyzed
before
any application was permitted.
And I think we have got the
guardrails in place to ensure that
what I say and what my members say is that we are responsible miners and
that
everything that we do now, we would continue to do, regardless of the scale
of the project or how much of the conservation
estate it is. And I know people think that Denniston Plateau is a very large area,
and it is. But relative to a third of the country, it's not.
So relative to the size of the conservation estate, it's still, again, a
small piece. So,
it's not this
miners coming in and taking over everything.
I really reject that kind of view that's being pushed out
there.
There's one
extension project
at the moment. So,
I
do think that all the rules and regulations in place and the many acts that have to
be abided by, by a mining project on the conservation estate, and the
existing protections in the law, that will not change if this
act is modernized,
give adequate cover.
Look, thank you very much, Josie. We have met time.
Thank you. Thank you so much for your questions.
And we really thank you for your submission and that perspective today.
It's really useful. So thank you.
Thank you.
So we now move to our next submission, who are joining us
online, and we can see you there. Genevieve, welcome to the
select committee this morning. You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand
it over to you to open up, and then we'll have some questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Chair. Tena koutou katoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
My name is Genevieve Toop, and I am representing on behalf of
Greenpeace Aotearoa. Unfortunately, I couldn't join you
in Wellington today. I've traveled up to Auckland because in just
two days' time, I'll be joining thousands of people
who will march down Queen Street against the Conservation
Amendment Bill.
Members of the committee,
you received more than 90,000 submissions on this
bill
from people from all walks of life.
And the fact is, every time a government threatens
conservation land,
thousands of people take to the streets to
defend it.
Why is that?
Well, I think the answer's pretty simple.
Public conservation land is an inseparable
part of who we are as New Zealanders
It is where we go tramping, hunting, and fishing,
where we take our kids camping,
where we find adventure and connection with the natural world.
And for Maori, it is ancestral land and waters.
I think we can all agree we are all proud to live on these
beautiful islands, defined by life that is found
nowhere else on Earth,
and spectacular landscapes that are truly the
envy of the world.
There is no question that our people have a
fierce and enduring love of these places.
That is why it is so surprising to me
that this government thought it wise, in an
election year,
to propose a bill
that attacks the conservation land that sits at
the heart of our nation
and is so cherished by our people.
A bill that asks New Zealanders to abandon our love of
conservation land and to wash our hands of the
responsibility we know we have to care for
it and protect it for those who come after us.
A bill that threatens every single local conservation
area in this country.
All the hunting blocks mates escape to for the weekend,
all the favorite camping areas families return to every summer,
all the local forest walks people use daily.
In this oral submission, I will outline how this bill strips
away critical protections for conservation land and
call on you to reject it in its entirety.
Firstly, Clause 6EA.
Never in all my years as an environmental
advocate have I come across such an
egregious proposal.
A proposal that says there is no part of the natural
world that should be protected from companies that
want to exploit it.
This clause upends the foundational premise that has
sat at the heart of our conservation law for
40 years.
On conservation land,
conservation is the point.
And I find it deeply troubling that I'm having to
explain this basic principle
to the very people entrusted
temporarily
with the custodianship of public conservation
lands.
The whole point of public conservation land is
that over generations we have recognized that human
activity can damage and destroy the natural world.
So we have collectively chosen, generation after
generation,
to set aside some places where nature comes first.
That doesn't mean it's locked away.
People can and do already run businesses on New Zealand's
conservation land. People can guide, film,
research, graze livestock,
operate tourism businesses, and unfortunately, still
even mine.
But there has always been a core purpose and a hierarchy.
Conservation comes first. Recreation is to be fostered and
tourism allowed where these activities are not inconsistent with
conservation.
The government's own analysis shows that of
2,810 concession applications in
2025, just 2% were declined.
This is not a system where reasonable commercial activity is
being locked out. The evidence does not support that
myth.
Yet Clause 6EA of this bill creates a new statutory
function requiring the Department of Conservation to
enable exploitation of conservation land to the
greatest extent practicable.
You cannot rewrite the law to enable corporations
to exploit conservation land to the greatest extent
practicable and still claim that land is protected.
If protection is no longer the purpose, it is no
longer conservation land in any meaningful sense.
So what this bill asks our people to accept is a
future where public conservation land in Aotearoa no longer
means land protected for nature and for the public to enjoy.
And I do not believe for a second that New Zealanders will accept that future,
because most people in this country understand
instinctively that this land, its forests, its
rivers, its wildlife,
all have an intrinsic, immeasurable value
purely because they exist,
not because a company can extract commercial profit from
them.
But it is not only Clause 6EA of this bill that is the issue.
This bill systematically strips away protections on conservation
land one by one, so that it would become easier for more open
cast mines and other inappropriate commercial exploitation to
invade and degrade Aotearoa's most treasured
wild places. For example, the bill proposes to
establish a new category of land known as visitor amenity areas.
That name makes it sound fairly innocuous.
A toilet, perhaps, a shelter at the end of a walking track.
That is not what is being proposed here.
I heard the previous submitter say that it was misinformation
being spread about strip malls. Well, I'd like to draw your
attention, members of the committee, to Clause 16A, which
lists out exactly the kind of commercial
infrastructure that can be established within these new visitor
amenity areas. It includes accommodation, car parks,
transportation, restaurants,
merchandising, and any other infrastructure
that supports visitor and recreational activities.
In plain language,
merchandising means shops, accommodation means
private resorts and multi-story hotels, and transportation
can mean monorails.
These are not visitor amenity areas.
These are commercial exploitation zones, and this bill proposes that
the minister could initiate one of these zones whenever they like
without a public hearing,
and even in the heart of our national parks.
Do you really think that Aucklanders want to see
private resorts on the shores of Rangitoto Island?
Do you think it's appropriate to build a McDonald's in Milford
Sound?
Do you think future generations will thank you when you took
places once set aside to protect their extraordinary and
unique natural values and turned them into tacky
theme parks?
If you agree these things are not appropriate,
then do not recommend a bill that makes them possible.
This bill also proposes to deregulate the concessions framework.
It strips important decision-making powers away from the public via
independent New Zealand Conservation Authority and local conservation
boards, and concentrates those powers with the minister.
And rather than place Te Tiriti o Waitangi at the heart of
our conservation system in Aotearoa, and ensure the
Crown upholds its obligations as a treaty partner,
this bill deliberately undermines the practical effect
of Section 4 of the Conservation Act.
So put those changes together. Number one, change the purpose of what
conservation land is for. Number two, create new pathways for commercial
development and deregulate the commercial permissions framework.
Number three, restrict the role of iwi and hapū in
decisions. And number four, concentrate decision-making
power with the minister of the day.
Taken together, those changes turn conservation
land from something we protect into something that can be
exploited and commercialized. And sure, the
committee has removed provisions that would have made it easier to sell
off up to five million
hectares of public conservation land.
But removing those clauses does not fix this bill.
So while you may have heard from some submitters that they believe this bill is
salvageable
if you make some amendments , I want to make something
categorically clear.
Greenpeace opposes this Conservation Amendment Bill in its entirety.
We are not here to negotiate over how much
degradation of conservation land is acceptable.
We are not here to concede that the fundamental purpose of
conservation land should be rewritten to accommodate greater
private commercial exploitation.
When it comes to the fundamental
principle
that conservation land exists first and foremost for conservation,
there can be no compromise.
And we will continue to stand alongside the tens of thousands
of people across Aotearoa who feel the same.
It is worth remembering that governments who have misjudged how deeply New
Zealanders cherish conservation land before have
learned their lesson fairly quickly.
In 2010, the John Key government proposed opening up
national parks to mining.
Faced with an enormous public response, John Key recognized that
political blunder and he backed down entirely.
The question for this government is whether its leader has the same political
nous to recognize the warning signs:
90,000 submissions,
thousands preparing to march, and an election looming.
Before I finish, I'd like to remind members of the select
committee,
conservation land does not belong
to this government.
In fact, it does not belong to any of us
because there are some things we cannot and do
not own in the ordinary sense of the word.
We are not owners of the forests that have stood for
centuries, of the rivers that have carved their way through land
over thousands of years, of native wildlife that
has evolved over millennia.
For the very short period of time that each of us is here,
these places and this wildlife is in our
care before we pass them on to the next generation.
That is the idea at the heart of conservation.
It is a promise we collectively make that what
has been protected by those who came before us will
remain protected for those who come after.
The Conservation Amendment Bill fundamentally breaks that
promise.
And the reason that matters so much
is that the decisions you make here will
outlast every person alive today.
Because governments come and go, members of parliament come and go,
but an ancient forest that is felled does not come back for
centuries. A species that becomes extinct and a
wild place destroyed by mines and commercial
development cannot simply be magicked back into
existence
That is why Greenpeace is not asking you to improve this bill.
We are asking you to reject it.
To make the same choice that generation after generation
of New Zealanders has made,
to continue to preserve and protect
conservation land. Thank you.
Thank you, Genevieve. Look, we don't have time for many questions, but we'll go
first to Grant McCallum.
Quick question. Genevieve, thank you for your submission.
Question I have is, do you see any circumstances under which
DOC could swap or sell or exchange land?
Well, I don't think that's what's being discussed on the table.
As I understand, the Select Committee has put a new bill forth that has removed
any land sale and exchange provisions.
Um-
But they do exist, they exist in the current bill, so-- in the, sorry, in the
current act. So I'm just saying, do you think there are any circumstances in which
the land can be swapped or sold?
I think the current act has sufficient safeguards against the
sale and exchange of land that has conservation values.
As you'll know, uh, the test is that before land can be sold or exchanged, it
has to have, uh, have been assessed, um, and have no to very
low conservation value. I think that's an appropriate safeguard, and I do
think that, uh, the depth of feeling that I'm sure you
noticed when the land sale and exchange provisions, uh, were
proposed, uh, by this government to make it easier to sell a five million hectares,
um, that people were not on board with that plan.
If you had wanted to get rid of some bits and bobs, it would've been very easy to
put a schedule in the bill and explicitly tell us what
those bits and bobs were-
Okay
... um, so that people could really have a look at that and decide whether or not
those bits and bobs could be sold or exchanged.
Thank you.
That was not happened. Um, and so yeah, we, we think
the existing safeguards are appropriate.
No, thank you, Genevieve. And as you've rightly pointed out, um, that section has
been taken out of the bill and, and represented.
So, um, we, uh, appreciate you acknowledging that.
So, thank you. We have met time. Um, and unfortunately we don't have
any further time for questions, but we do appreciate your submission today, so
thank you.
Thanks.
So we now move to our next submitter, who is also online with us,
um, Environment Southland. Uh, we can
see you there, Jeremy. Welcome to the Select Committee today.
Your 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand it over to you.
Okay. Thank you. You can hear me all right?
Yes.
Very good. And, uh, welcome from a, uh, very wet Southland
at the moment. Um, look, thank you, Chair and members of the committee, for the
oppor- opportunity to present Southland's perspective on these
important reforms. Uh, my name's Jeremy McPhail, chair of
Environment Southland. And with me, I take it, we have,
uh, Mar- Marcus and Shana, uh, who are, uh,
uh, from our strategy and policy team, who are probably the
intellectuals in the, in our, our, uh- ...
in the capacity here, so they can answer some of the technical questions.
We're supported, um, no, Environment Southland- ...
is responsible for the integrated man- management of natural and physical
resources and for m- maintaining indigenous biodiversity
across Southland, working in enduring partnership with mana whenua
and our communities. Environment Southland supports sustainable
tourism and other appropriate economic activi-
activities where they are compatible with the protection and the
enhancement of conservation values.
And with that context, I'll hand over to Marcus, and he can outline
the, uh, couple of key issues we wish to highlight today.
Hopefully Marcus is here.
Yeah.
Yeah, thank you, um, Jeremy. I'll start with the first issue.
Hey, Shana.
Yeah. Um, so we support the intent of these reforms.
It is clear that the current framework is outdated and is overly
burdensome in some respects. However, our key message is this:
the bill needs to be amended to ensure that economic objectives remain
subordinate to the overarching purpose of conservation, and that local
expertise and system integrity are not undermined.
You have our full written submission.
Today we will focus on two issues that we believe are critical to whether this
reform succeeds. Um, issue one is the purpose
of the Conservation Act. The core purpose of the conservation
framework is to protect and preserve nature and historic
resources for future generations.
This is strongly supported by Southland communities, who have a
deep connection to natural heritage in our region.
We support the introduction of an economic objective in
theory. In reality, that could elevate development to the
same status as conservation objectives.
Uh, this, uh, must be avoided. Otherwise, um, conflicting
signals will cause delay and confusion to natural management.
Um, for example, a targeted international visitor access charge in
heavy traffic areas could provide useful revenue,
but a defined proportion of that income should be assigned to
conservation, um, in that area to show what is being
protected.
Uh, local authorities should be involved in the design of that process.
We also support, in principle, visitor amenities areas
to help coordinate infrastructure in high traffic areas like
Piopiotahi, Milford Sound. But without safeguards,
uh, visitor amenities areas could also cause significant
risks to sensitive habitats.
Here we must emphasize the importance of local environmental knowledge to
the success of these proposals. The bill needs clarification
reaffirming conservation as the overriding purpose of the system.
Economic objectives are a helpful but subordinate enabler.
And with that, I'll pass to Marcus.
Thanks, Shana. The second significant issue we wanna raise is around early
local and regional engagement. So whilst we recognize the importance of
streamlining in several areas, the bill proposes
to reduce opportunity for local input
It's disappointing that the bill insufficiently recognizes the role
local government plays in conservation.
Regional councils undertake significant duties
of the natural and physical environment, including biosecurity risks,
biodiversity, discharge of contaminated water, water takes, and
sediment runoff.
Ultimately, as costs are borne by regional ratepayers, councils should
have a greater say in designing regulatory frameworks on
conservation land.
Earlier and more meaningful engagement is an essential part of
legitimate decision-making.
For example, changes to the concession system should require early
consultation with local authorities to prevent environmental
risks.
Broader changes, like increased ministerial direction and reduced
roles for the New Zealand Conservation Authority and conservation boards,
may limit the diversity of perspectives informing decision-making.
This is likely to reduce the influence of iwi and hapū perspectives within the
conservation system.
We recommend a correction to these oversights,
amending the bill to require early engagement with key stakeholders,
including local government, on significant decisions for key functions.
We should not change our long-term biosecurity by overlooking
local expertise for the sake of centralized decision-making.
We acknowledge the critical role that tangata whenua play in the
stewardship of conservation land.
Treaty principles should continue to be given full effect to in
conservation and decision-making.
And it's worth noting, before I hand back to Jeremy, that in a Southland context,
over 50% of the Southland region is
held and administered by the Department of Conservation, so it is a huge
proportion of
Southland's land estate. So, I'll hand back to Jeremy to close us out before
questions.
Yeah, thank you, Marcus and Shana.
To draw together the points made by my team here,
modernization of the conservation framework is welcome
and necessary. We encourage a broader framing of
conservation to go beyond just preservation towards wider
environmental socioeconomic outcomes.
But we would caution the committee on proposed reforms that
go too far in the name of centralized streamlining.
In summary, we ask that you allow local and regional authorities
to continue to protect unique habitats by engaging our
expertise early. We have highlighted two issues, the purpose of the
Conservation Act and early local and
regional engagement. Targeting these issues is crucial to
achieving the overall aims of the conservation framework.
We must remember not to undervalue intangible benefits from our
natural spaces and maintain balance when unlocking
financial opportunities.
Targeted amendments can unlock economic potential while
safeguarding our precious environment for future generations.
So, we thank you, and we welcome your questions.
Thank you for that submission. We've got a few questions.
We'll go first to Rachel Brooking.
Thank you. And thank you for your appendix too.
I thought that was very interesting.
I'm interested in some of the comments Marcus was making as well, and particularly
the interaction with the Resource Management Act as it is,
because, of course,
well, you can explain this better than me, but the Resource Management
Act doesn't apply to some activities happening on conservation land.
Obviously, you're Environment Southland, you're the regional council,
and a whole lot of your area is
Fiordland, which is a beautiful national park.
So, I'm interested in how you
think
regional councils should be working with
the Department of Conservation. If everything was working well with the RMA
as it is,
what's your relationships then with DOC in
Fiordland? And
all of these things that you've got in the boxes, the potential
impacts of proposed reforms,
are they things that could be addressed under the RMA,
or does it
completely have to be in the conservation
legislation for these things to be considered?
Yeah, this is a really great question, and particularly given the role of
regional spatial planning moving forward.
So,
a number of the conservation management
plans haven't been reviewed on time, so they are getting quite
old, and there's a significant opportunity here with the regional spatial planning
approach to have a consistent, coordinated
planning and policy framework for
the whole region of Southland, including Rakiura National
Park and Fiordland National Park, to have that consistency and coordination
across economy, tourism,
environment, productive capacity and use of
land, and industry, including the marine space.
So, there's a really strong opportunity in that spatial planning to bring
together those conservation components that need strategic
regional decision-making, and
the combined regulatory planning framework could assist
with
the use and development concessions.
There's very similar components associated with those decision-makings.
So, there is similarities in the current Conservation Act concession
process with the resource consent decision process,
and future decisions could be more aligned.
But I think the underlying purpose of our submission is that the conservation
estate is owned by the Crown, and it needs to have
those values associated with the
conservation estate protected in the first instance.
Yes, and you've made that point very well. Thank you.
Thank you. Yeah, really useful. Look, we'll go to Grant McCullagh, and then
Celia.
Just very quickly.
You'll have heard some people come out and say, "Oh, the whole bill's a crock and
we've got to get rid of it." Any response to that from your perspective?
I'll try and answer that.
Look, there's a balance, and I know this is
probably... I look at it, and it's about funding
issues, and we've got some serious issues down south here, and
we're
realistic with some of this discussion.
We're supportive of it, but it is still conservation land.
We don't want to see a
continual eroding of our precious
environment in regards to that, but there is a balance, and we do
have bills to pay.
And we have indicated that in our submission.
It's not about just taking the money to Wellington either.
If there is money, if it's funding, it needs to be spent where it is
made, and Milford is a very important site for
that sort of funding.
So,
in
today's view, there has to be balances on this, but
I'm probably a wee bit concerned even myself in regards to having
ministerial...
A minister can decide on things, and that's where we say this is local
and regional
input needs to be put into this. We don't want to see just Wellington come along
and say, "You're having this in Milford or on Rakiura Island,"
because you've got to bring the community along on these things.
But it's about funding, and
we do need the funding. We are short of the funding, especially down south
here in regards to these things.
Thanks very much. Appreciate
it.
Hopefully that answers that a wee bit. Yeah.
Thank you. Celia.
Kia ora. Thanks for the work you do in the Regional Council.
I was interested in how you thought the
Southland Conservation Board could be
potentially strengthened, or the relationship with the Southland Regional
Council.
What areas for improvement, rather than just
reducing their input?
Do you have meetings with the
Southland Conservation Board?
We do know who's on it. Do we have meetings?
I would have to ask staff in regards to that
with around the council interaction with the Conservation Board.
Marcus, can I just quickly throw that to you?
Yeah.
We are connected with them, probably not as closely as we should.
A lot of it is around that policy development space, and as I say, the
conservation management plans and strategies are a little bit behind.
So yeah, there's definitely room and opportunity for more connection to be better
represented. But I think in terms of the parties around the table on those
conservation boards, they come from a diverse range of perspectives.
You've got tourism in there, you've got local iwi and hapū in there, you've got
professionals, you've got industry, and you've got conservationists.
So the
diversity on those groups leads to robust conversations
and well-considered outcomes.
And
sorry, I was just going to add and quite add that we do know who's on that.
I know we've had councillors, ex-councillors on that board.
And Southland's a very small community, so we do know, we do talk about
and engage with a lot of stakeholders
in this area.
Yeah, just to add to that-
Thank you. I look forward to seeing you in Fiordland.
Yeah.
Thank you. Cameron.
It'll be real quick. Just housekeeping of it.
Marcus, on the cover letter, it says it hasn't gone to full council, this
submission. Has it now?
Yes, it has gone through full council retrospectively.
Thank you.
And just a quick question from Lam.
Oh, kia ora. Thank you so much for this fantastic submission.
My question was just around
your
suggestion about a cumulative threshold or a
percentage that could be put in the bill.
I assume so that it stops any sort of
wild swings in terms of land disposal, all that kind of thing.
Do you want to expand a little bit on that?
Marcus?
If I might give it a go.
So yeah, we had a clear indication from staff
members within the organization that there are some land
currently held as conservation land that can be
turned into non-conservation land for practical reasons, if
they were only held for admin purposes.
But we would want to ensure that
any process is run with transparency.
That's why we proposed some sort of formula
that can be used to undertake the process.
In terms of the specifics, I guess that is up for discussion,
but any discussion will need
to involve local input, as Jeremy has explained earlier.
We would want to
increase the chance of successful outcome by ensuring the local expertise and
knowledge will be used in the process.
Look, thanks. That's really interesting.
Thank you very much for your submission this morning.
Yeah, really useful information, really valuable submission, so thank you.
Thank you.
So that brings us to the end of our public submissions this
morning for this morning's session on the Conservation Amendment Bill.
We will now move into private session